Guide to the Rita Sanchez Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Rita Sanchez papers
1953-2003
SC0768
Sanchez, Rita.
3.5 Linear feet 5 boxes
Papers pertain to her education at Stanford University, her teaching career at San Diego Mesa College, her interest in Chicano/Chicana artists and activists and Chicano history, and her own writings. Included are class papers, articles, correspondence, publications, audio and videotapes, journals, photographs, and other materials.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of English and Chicano Studies at San Diego Mesa College, Rita Sanchez earned three degrees at Stanford: her bachelor's (1972) and master's (1974) in English and a master's in education in 1973.
Description of the Collection
Papers pertain to her education at Stanford University, her teaching career at San Diego Mesa College, her interest in Chicano/Chicana artists and activists and Chicano history, and her own writings. Included are class papers, articles, correspondence, publications, audio and videotapes, journals, photographs, and other materials.
Access Terms
Mexican Americans--Study and teaching.; Mexican Americans.; San Diego Mesa College--Faculty.; San Diego Mesa College. -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Sanchez, Rita.; Mexican Americans--Study and teaching.; Mexican Americans.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2005-250
  - Pre-Stanford Years: San Bernardino Junior High School, Sturges Jr. High 1951-1952, Editor of the Year Book 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - San Bernardino High School: High School Reunion 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - San Bernardino High School: Assistant Editor Tyro Weekly Newspaper 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - SBHS A Capella Choir with Dutch Hauschildt 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - High School Grad Award: "50 Top Seniors Chosen" 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rita's Addresses while at Stanford (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stanford Vita and Recommendation (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stanford Vita 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Stanford 1974 M.A. English taught Freshman English course: Chicano/a Perspective (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Extras: Stanford Posters (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writings for Arturo Islas, Stanford 1970. and others (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Papers written at Stanford (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chicano Student Journals, edited by Arthur Islas, Stanford, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stanford Daily February 6, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stanford Daily July 28, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stanford Observer May 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chicanismo Stanford 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stanford Teaching Credential, Graduation Announcement, news articles 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Chicana Writer Breaking Out of Silence 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Stanford Committee Assistant to the President for Chicano Affairs (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1974 El Malcriado UFW Newspaper UFW Movement (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cesar Chavez Tapes 1973 SDSU (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Poster for Recruiting Chicanos 974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - La Chicana Course 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Journals Edited with Stanford and SDSU 1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - De Colores Journal: La Cosecha, 1977, info on folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Committee Assistant to the President for Chicano Affairs—Hiring of Cecilia Burciega—20 years later (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Stanford Reunion 2002 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - San Diego State University: becomes full professor 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Evaluations (titled Curriculum Vita 1992) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Vita 1992 and Credential Record (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ford Foundation Fellowship Award 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Development Award 1979—6 units release time (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Articles on students writing in course with Prof. Rita Sanchez (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Art Articles 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Chicano Gallery Opens" March 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - List of Articles published as Guest Writer (single paper) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Articles by RS, 1981 Newsline (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper articles on Corita Kent (1985), Domingo Ulloa, Mario Torero (1979), Judith Hernandez (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ulloa: Artistic Triumph of Chicano Art 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Corita Billboard to Rise Again" Jan. 7, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mural Art Articles 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Article on 3 murals by Mario Torero 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - RS and husband Mario Acevedo articles 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letras y colores 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Writings on Artists 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Las Commadres Centro Cultural 1990 trying to write an essay (Box 2)
  - Typed Originals of Art Articles 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Chicano Park 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Rita's Sabbatical (not awarded) 1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sabbatical Proposal Awarded 1997 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - San Diego Community College District Application for Sabbatical Leave (Box 2)
  - La Frida (unpublished paper on Frida Kahlo) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Interview w/ Rita Sanchez as Union Member (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Evaluations—includes folder Letters from Students (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Days of the Dead, Mesa College, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Chicana Feminist Thought, Rita Sanchez evaluation (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Chicana writing materials from Charlotte—includes video of Sanchez' response to Rodney King incident and written speech (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Coalition against Racism 1992 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Speeches at Mesa—"After Rodney King Incident" 1992 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Coalition Against Racism (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Mesa College, San Diego—Assessing Campus Climate (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 25th Anniversary Speech Written speech and video (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - SDSU 30th Anniversary (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Presentation, San Diego Festival of Colors, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Chicano Park Tour 1998 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - On Teaching Gloria Anzaldua (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Dolores Huerta—Cesar Chavez Day--2003 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Nominee for San Diego County Women's Hall of Fame (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Chicano Studies Department Review 2002 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Tapes from the 70s: Cesar Chavez, Dolores Huerta, Tomas Ybarra Frausto, Chicano Conferences, etc. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - envelope from Stanford Registrar—contains teaching credential (Box 3)
  - empty manila envelope (Box 3)
  - Code of Ethics of the Teaching Profession (Box 3)
  - Presenter, Many Voices (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Las Madrinas Mentor, Community Mentoring Program (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Red Folder: No More Wars, Human Rights (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - National Association for Chicana/o Studies Annual Conference 2001 (Box 3)
  - More Presentations 1989-2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Women Writers Humanities Program 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Inland Empire Bookfest presents Cochise remembers, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Speech at UNAM Presentation: Aztlan Reocupado (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - US Latinos and World War II (Box 3)
  - Short Story Contest 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chicano Lit Contest, 1983—Fragmentos de Barro (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - California Lit Project, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - SD Writing Project (empty) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Honors Program Letter (Box 3)
  - blue folder: Genealogical Society of Hispanic America 14th Annual Conference, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1996-2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Publication 1997, "Commentary: Corrido de Cesar" in Aztlan, Chicano Culture (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Border Passion: World Crossover to Selena" in Aztlan: Chicano Culture, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Rita's Book Cochise Remembers My Great-Grandfather: Charles Henry Coleman, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Maize 1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Publications 2000-2005, contains 2 folders: On Rita's Book, Cochise Remembers, and Journal Publications 200-2005 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Letters of Acceptance for Publication in Anthology Latinos and Latinas in World War II (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 2 VHS cassettes: Cesar Chavez Day at San Diego Mesa College, 4/1/2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The Mesa Press, April 8, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Utopia Now: Myth and Folklore in Chicano Literature, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
  - Utopian Elements in Rodolfo Anaya's Heart of Aztlan (Box 3)
  - Funeteovejuna: Una Obra Tradicional y Revolucionaria, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Rita's Writings, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - 2 copies of Vision 1976 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - poem drafts (Box 3)
  - Rita's Journals, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Flashbacks/Stories/Writings (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Rita's Writings on the Arts, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Acevedo Art Gallery Inventory 1990s (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Acevedo Gallery 1986 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - news articles in white paper (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Physical and Spiritual Recovery (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Yrena Cervantez, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Materials on artists, not much correspondence:
    - Acevedo Gallery (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Gallery Invitations (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Art Auction 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - manila envelope containing material on gallery (Box 4)
    - Acevedo Gallery International, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Art Articles, Acevedo Art Gallery, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Contracts, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Press Releases, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Guillermo Acevedo (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Mario Torero Acevedo, 1979-1989, includes photos (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Mario Cespedes 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Mario Cespedes 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Sonya Fe—includes photos and negatives (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Rupert Garcia (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Willie Herron, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Corita Kent, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Miguel Martinez 1983-1987—includes photos and negatives (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Tony Ortega, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Robert Lentz and Nathaniel Hauser, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Robert Miles Parker, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Lilly Rosa and Gary Hansmann 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Jacqueline Rochester, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Frank Romero, 1987-1988, includes slides (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Domingo Ulloa, 1981-1986 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Zarco, 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Misc. art and artists 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Artists Gallery, 1978-1988 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Photo Album of Acevedo Gallery publicity flyers, 1984-1989 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Guestbook to Gallery 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - manila folder on top: 2 letters (1984, 1989) and San Diego City Magazine p. 73-74 (Box 4)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH.2013-012
  - La Chicana (Short Articles), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stanford Graduation and photos, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rita's Stanford Grad Announcements, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rita's Stanford Grad Announcements, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notes, 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Embracing Indian Ancestry, New Mexico Genealogist, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Southern New Mexico Historical Review publications by Rita, 2001, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chicano Park Female Artists article (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rita's retirement plaque and Chicano Studies sign, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rita Sanchez presents on Frida Kahlo at Women Who Dare (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Honoring Betita Martinez at Mesa College (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rita invited Delores Huerta to San Diego, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mesa College Program Review, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New Publications (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Journal Entries (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Barack Obama Inaguaral Album, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rita's Activities at SDSU (pamphlets, flyers), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Certificates of recognition (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photo of Rita's SDSU Chicana Class, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rita at San Bernadino High School (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Engagement and Wedding Clippings (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photos - High School, Engagement, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Five Sanchez Brothers (proof) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - WWII Story (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Attu Story, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Stanford Magazine, 2009, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sanchez Family Research (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - San Diego Women's Hall of Fame (flyer) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - San Diego Women's Hall of Fame (program) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - San Diego Women's Hall of Fame (congratulatory cards) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - San Diego Women's Hall of Fame (congratulations from Toni Atkins) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - San Diego Women's Hall of Fame (article) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - San Diego Women's Hall of Fame (notes) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - San Diego Women's Hall of Fame (invitation) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - San Diego Women's Hall of Fame (barrio station recognition) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - WWII - Sanchez Brothers (Box 1, Folder 36)